Guide to the Giles Family Papers 1750-1851 MS 248
New-York Historical Society
Giles family papers
1750-1851
New-York Historical Society
MS 248
0.4 Linear feet (1 box)
The Giles Family Papers consists primarily of papers belonging to Aquila and Elizabeth Shipton Giles, their descendants, and their extended family, including correspondence, love letters between Aquila Giles and Elizabeth Shipton Giles, accounts, leases, surveys, commissions, bills, receipts, and notes. The majority of the correspondence covers the courtship of Aquila Giles and Elizabeth Shipton Giles during the American Revolution, but the collection also includes papers pertaining to Aquila Giles's military service and the business transactions of William Axtell, John Murray, and William Ogden, all of whom were related to the Giles family.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Aquila Giles was born in Maryland in 1758 to Jacob and Joanna Paca Giles. His grandfather was the Maryland governor, William Paca. During the American Revolution he joined the Continental Army, eventually rising to the rank of Major under General Arthur St. Clair. He was taken prisoner and paroled in New York City, where he met and married Elizabeth Shipton in October of 1780. At the time of their meeting, Elizabeth was living at the home of her uncle, William Axtell, a Loyalist. The couple settled in Maryland and had 10 children, 8 of whom survived infancy.
In the early 1800s, Aquila Giles became involved in a legal dispute over land with the U.S. Government, which lasted for several years. Subsequent financial difficulties forced Elizabeth to return to England in 1812, with her youngest son, George Washington Giles. Aquila eventually won his lawsuit and was employed as a U.S. Army store keeper in 1817. Elizabeth Shipton and Aquila Giles both died in 1822.
George Washington Giles became a lawyer and married Elizabeth Ogden, the daughter of William Ogden and Susan Murray Ogden. John and Hannah Murray were Elizabeth Ogden Giles's uncle and aunt.
Scope and Content Note
The Giles Family Papers consists primarily of correspondence between Aquila Giles and Elizabeth Shipton Giles during their courtship. Although these letters were written during the American Revolution, they are notable for the fact that they make virtually no mention of current events, but focus almost entirely on the couple's relationship and their feelings for one another. The collection also contains the business transactions and correspondence of their sons, Henry and George Washington Giles, William Axtell (Elizabeth Shipton Giles's uncle), and several relatives of Elizabeth Ogden Giles (wife of George Washington Giles), William Ogden and John Murray.
Also included in the collection are letters detailing Henry Giles's suspension from West Point, the Ordnance Papers of Aquila Giles, correspondence between Elizabeth Shipton Giles and Lords Clarendon and Cathcart upon her return to England in 1812, and a receipt for the purchase of a male slave by a William Smithe in 1783.
Arrangement
The Giles Family papers are organized in the following five series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence, 1779-1851
Series 2: Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1763-1821
Series 3: Legal Documents, 1750-1841
Series 4: Ordnance Papers of Aquila Giles, 1818-1822
Series 5: Personal Documents, 1795-1816
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Additional material related to the Giles Family:
The John Murray Papers
The Schenk Family Papers
The Matthias B. Tallmadge Papers
American loyalists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bonds (legal records).; Commissions (orders for works).; Correspondence.; Courtship; Deeds.; Invoices.; Love letters.; Military supplies -- New York (State).; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 18th century.; Ordnance.; Receipts (financial records); United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; Young women -- Social life and customs -- 18th century.; Axtell, William, 1720-1795; Cathcart, William Schaw Cathcart, Earl, 1755-1843; Villiers, John Charles, 1757-1822; Giles, Aquila, -1822; Giles, Elizabeth Shipton, 1758-1822; Giles, Henry, 1795-; John Murray & Sons; Murray, John, 1737-1808; Ogden, William; Scott, Juliana; White, Matthew; United States Military Academy; United States. Army -- Ordnance and ordnance stores
- Series I: Correspondence, 1779-1851
  Scope and Contents note
  This series primarily includes correspondence between Elizabeth Shipton Giles and Aquila Giles, the majority of which was written during their courtship. There are also letters from Lords Clarendon and Cathcart to Elizabeth Shipton Giles, letters from Matthew White to Elizabeth Shipton Giles, letters from Juliana Scott to Aquila Giles, and letters to Henry Giles concerning his suspension from West Point.
  - Correspondence sent to Aquila Giles by Elizabeth Shipton Giles, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence sent to Aquila Giles by Elizabeth Shipton Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence sent to Aquila Giles by Sally Broome with a postscript by Elizabeth Shipton Giles, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence sent to Aquila Giles by Juliana Scott, 1800-1801 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence sent to Aquila Giles by Cordelia Giles, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to Aquila Giles, 1784-1821 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to Aquila Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence sent by Aquila Giles to Henry Giles, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles by Aquila Giles, 1780-1784 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles by Aquila Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles by Edmund Digby, 1809-1812 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles by Lord Cathcart, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles by Lord Clarendon, 1812-1813 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles by Matthew White, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to Elizabeth Shipton Giles, 1780-1813 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to Henry Giles, 1815-1822 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to Henry Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to George Washington Giles, 1819-1837 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to George Washington Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to William Ogden, 1799-1823 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Assorted correspondence sent by William Ogden, 1802-1825 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Assorted correspondence sent to John Murray, 1811-1831 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Unsigned Note, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Invitations sent to Aquila Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Invitation sent to Curtis Giles, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Envelopes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series 2: Accounts, Bills, and Receipts, 1763-1821
  Series 2 consists of accounts, bills, and receipts pertaining to various transactions and payments made by and to Aquila Giles, William Ogden, William Axtell, and Elizabeth Shipton Giles. Most notably, the series contains a receipt from June 27, 1783 relating to the sale of a slave to a William Smithe of Cumberland Forge.
  - Receipt pertaining to William Axtell, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Accounts, bills, and receipts pertaining to Aquila Giles, 1786-1821 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Accounts, bills, and receipts pertaining to William Ogden, 1798-1819 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Receipts pertaining to Elizabeth Shipton Giles, 1812-1815 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Assorted accounts, bills, and receipts, 1783-1819 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series 3: Legal Documents, 1750-1841
  Series 3 consists primarily of documents pertaining to the business and land dealing of Aquila Giles, William Axtell, the Ogden family, and the Murray family. This includes an indenture made between Aquila Giles and his son, William Axtell Giles in 1810 and also documents witnessed by Aquila Giles in his capacity as a lawyer. This series also contains a survey of land on the Susquehana River owned by Aquila Giles, pension information pertaining to Aquila Giles, a document asserting the legitimacy of the marriage between Aquila Giles and Elizabeth Shipton Giles, and George Washington Giles's certificate of admittance by the Bar of New York.
  - Legal documents pertaining to William Axtell, 1763-1787 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Legal documents pertaining to Aquila Giles, 1795-1817 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Legal documents pertaining to George Washington Giles, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Legal document pertaining to Elizabeth Ogden Giles, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Legal documents pertaining to the Ogden family, 1763-1815 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Legal documents pertaining to John and Hannah Murray, 1808-1822 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Assorted mortgages, leases, and other legal documents, 1750-1825 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Survey of land belonging to Aquila Giles, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - List of papers belonging to the estate of Jacob Giles, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Pension information pertaining to Aquila Giles, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - George Washington Giles's admittance to the Bar of New York, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Proof of marriage between Aquila Giles and Elizabeth Shipton Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Series 4: Ordnance Papers of Aquila Giles, 1818-1822
  Series 4 consists of the Ordnance Papers of Aquila Giles, created when he was a U.S. Army shopkeeper. They contain detailed accounts of various goods and supplies that were sold, returned, or delivered.
  - Ordnance Papers of Aquila Giles, 1818-1822 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Ordnance Papers of Aquila Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Series 5: Personal Documents, 1795-1816
  Series 5 consists of various personal documents relevant to the Giles family, including the military commissions of Aquila Giles, passports belonging to William Axtell Giles and George Washington Giles, poetry (the majority of which was written by Aquila Giles for Elizabeth Shipton Giles), and an undated image of Aquila Giles.
  - Commissions of Aquila Giles, 1795-1800 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Passports of William Axtell Giles and George Washington Giles, 1800-1816 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Poetry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Image of Aquila Giles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)